Hey guys, it's
Christina, one of your
academic medicine
scholars for this year.
So today I'll be talking
about clinical hypertension,
and this is part one
of a two-part lecture.
And I want to give a
big thank you to Dr.
Murad for all her
guidance in creating this
lecture, as well as all
of the prior scholars
who have worked on
this lecture before me.
The session objectives
are going to include
developing a strategy
to screen, diagnose,
and stage hypertension,
demonstrating
the role of risk
factors in hypertension,
explaining the basic
pathophysiology of hypertension,
hypertension's
various forms, and the
pathologic complications
that come with it.
so let's start off with a
case presentation so we have
a 65 year old black male
with a history of type 2
diabetes mellitus and
osteoarthritis presenting to the
clinic with complaints of
headaches he's on ibuprofen
and metformin he has a family
history of heart failure
and hypertension he lives a
sedentary lifestyle rarely
exercises has a stressful
job where he works long
hours and so his diet
consists of mostly fast food.
He's been smoking for 35 years
and has two beers a night.
He says he measures his
blood pressure at home and
it's 140 over 80. He brought
his cuff with him today.
And here we have all
the vitals for our
patient. So heart rate
is 97 beats per minute.
Temperature is 98.2
degrees Fahrenheit.
Respiratory rate is
14 beats per minute.
Blood pressure is 145
over 92 in the left
arm and 143 over 91
in the right arm.
Height is 6 feet. Weight
is 250 and BMI is 35.9. So
I want you guys to start
thinking about this patient.
Looking back on the
previous slide, what kind
of risk factors are
you able to identify?
Kind of look through
the vitals and see
if you see anything
that's abnormal.
And just start thinking
about overall, what are
some things you would be
concerned about for this
patient? What would you
consider to start doing?
So let's dive into
what the actual
definition of hypertension is.
So I made a little
chart for you guys.
A normal range is
considered to be a systolic
of less than 120 and
a diastolic of less
than 80, elevated is
going to be a systolic of
120 to 129, and a
diastolic of less than 80.
Hypertension stage 1 is
considered a systolic
of 130 to 139, and a
diastolic of 80 to 89.
And then hypertension
stage 2 is considered a
systolic of greater than
or equal to 140, and
a diastolic of greater
than or equal to 90.
So these cutoffs are
based on the most recent
guidelines from 2017 from
the American College of
Cardiology and American Heart
Association. But just keep
in mind that these guidelines
have changed in the
past and they can continue
to change. So it's
important for you guys as
you move on to clinical
rotations to just stay be
mindful and stay up to date
on the most recent guidelines
that are out there.
And also if you find that
there's a disparity in
categories between your
systolic and diastolic
pressures, you're going to
go with the higher value
to determine the stage.
So for example, let's
say you have a systolic
that's in the normal range,
but then the diastolic
that's in the hypertension
stage 1 range, you're
going to go ahead and
diagnose the patient with
a hypertension stage 1.
So next let's talk about
the epidemiology. So
hypertension is a major risk
factor for heart disease
and stroke, which are both
leading causes of death
in the United States. If
you guys look at the map on
the right-hand side of the
page, you can see there's
a pretty clear geographic
distribution as to
where there's highest
prevalence of hypertension. So
mostly in that southeast
region of the U.S., and
this is from the CDC website
most recent from 2021.
About 50% of adults
greater than the age of 20
years old have hypertension,
so that means that
they're either on an
antihypertensive medication or
they had a systolic of
greater than or equal to 130
and a diastolic of greater
than or equal to 80.
About one in four adults
have controlled hypertension.
It accounts for 1.3
million visits to the
emergency department in
the United States every
year. And it's considered
to be a silent killer.
Silent because
many times patients
are going to be asymptomatic.
And it's usually something
that's incidentally
found on some kind
of screening, which
makes screening so
important for this.
But it's a silent
killer because it
doubles the risk of
cardiovascular disease.
And it's associated
with some pretty bad
pathologies such as strokes,
myocardial infarctions,
heart failure, aortic
dissections, aortic aneurysms.
And so deaths per 100,000 U
.S. population from essential
hypertension and hypertensive
renal disease is 13.
so to diagnose hypertension
is going to be a little
more involved than just an
initial screening and it
requires two or more readings
on two or more occasions and
ideally those occasions
will be readings from both
in and out of the office and
you're going to want to be
using appropriate technique
and cuff size which is
something that you guys
learned in your dpr class and
can feel free to like read
up on again and review so
there are a few ways to actually
measure the blood pressure
the first of which is
going to be office blood
pressure measurement so for
this you know some offices
have those automated cuff
devices or you could just take
the blood pressure manually
like you all learned in
DPR. So, of course, that
manual method is going to be
the most accurate blood
pressure reading that you'll
get. Then there's the home
blood pressure measurement.
So, that's through those
like usually like store
-bought automated devices
that people can use at home.
And then there's the
ambulatory blood pressure
measurement. So, this is a
device that the patient can
wear for 24 to 48 hours.
And we'll talk a little bit
more later in this lecture
about when that would be
indicated. But basically,
this cuff stays on for a
longer period of time and
measures the blood pressure
about every 20 minutes during
the day and about every
hour at night. But it
does have its limitations.
It's a little more expensive.
And it also depends on if
the physician knows how
to analyze the data
that's coming in through
the cuff. And it could also
be pretty uncomfortable
for the patient to just
keep that on for 24 to
48 hours. So just some
things to keep in mind.
According to the most
recent guidelines
in 2021 from the
U.S. Preventative
Service Task Force
recommendations,
it's advised to screen for
hypertension in adults 18
years or greater with
an office blood pressure
measurement at a minimum yearly
in adults with normal blood
pressure, and then at least
twice a year in adults
with risk factors like
obesity or type 2 diabetes
or those with prior elevated
systolic blood pressure.
So now we'll go into
the different types
of hypertension. So
we'll talk about primary,
also known as
essential hypertension,
secondary, white coat,
masked, resistant,
and then lastly we'll
talk about hypertensive
crisis which can
be further categorized
into either hypertensive
urgency or
hypertensive emergency.
Primary or essential
hypertension is going to account
for about 90% of hypertension,
and it's considered
to be primary because
there's no clear cause.
It's thought to be due to
some kind of interaction
between environmental
and genetic factors, and
many times it's familial.
It's considered to be
a silent killer because,
like I mentioned before,
patients are usually
going to be asymptomatic,
so it's usually
found upon screening
in an office blood
pressure measurement.
So let's talk a little
bit about the pathogenesis
of primary hypertension.
So largely it's
related to either an
increased cardiac output
or increased total
peripheral resistance. So
if you guys remember
your physiology formulas,
mean arterial pressure
equals cardiac output
times total peripheral
resistance. So
increasing that cardiac
output or increasing that
total peripheral
resistance is going to
lead to an increased
mean arterial pressure.
Then we have cardiac
output equals heart rate
times stroke volume. So
again, if you increase
the heart rate or if
you increase the stroke
value, you increase
the cardiac output and
in turn increase the
mean arterial pressure.
So a lot of this stems
from the renin angiotensin
aldosterone system. So
we'll quickly review
that and how that happens
and leads to increased
blood pressure. So you
have angiotensinogen that's
converted into angiotensin
1 from renin. And
things that are going to
stimulate renin are going
to be detection of
decreased blood pressure,
decreased sodium delivery
to the macula dents of
the kidney, and increased
sympathetics. So then
angiotensin 1 gets converted
to angiotensin 2 from
angiotensin converting
enzyme. And then And
angiotensin 2 has a couple
of different effects on
the body. So the first is
increasing sympathetics.
So increased sympathetics
is going to lead to
increased heart rate.
It leads to increased
contractility, which will
increase the stroke volume.
And so increased heart
rate and increased stroke
volume are going to
increase the cardiac output.
Then angiotensin 2 could
also increase aldosterone
secretion from the adrenal
glands and increased
anti-diuretic hormone
release from the posterior
pituitary of the hypothalamus.
So both of these things
are going to increase
sodium and water retention
in the vasculature system,
and that's going to
increase blood volume, and
that's going to increase
preload, which increases
stroke volume and leads to
increased cardiac output.
So all of these things
are going to lead to an
increased blood pressure.
Additionally,
all of these things, so
the increased angiotensin
2, increased sympathetics,
increased antidiuretic
hormone, increased
aldosterone, they lead
to more vasoconstriction,
and that's going to
lead to increased total
peripheral resistance.
And like we mentioned
before, that directly
leads to an increased
blood pressure.
Now, increased blood
pressure in and of
itself causes some
vascular remodeling,
increased endothelin,
decreased vasodilators.
So that's going to lead to
further vasoconstriction,
which further increases that
total peripheral resistance,
leading to even more
increased blood pressure.
So next we'll talk about
secondary hypertension.
This is going to account
for the remaining 10
% of hypertension, and
it's considered to be
secondary because there's
some known underlying
cause to the high blood
pressure, and it's
something that we could
potentially find and fix.
So there are certain patients
we're going to consider
this more so in. So if
there's a patient that has
hypertension but is unresponsive
to their medications,
if the patient is presenting
at a very young age, any
older patients that have
a new onset hypertension,
and any acute worsening
of patients who
previously had well
-controlled blood pressure.
so then for the
causes a lot of these
pathologies you guys
are going to learn
more so next semester
but they're here just so
that you know when you
look back you're aware
of the different causes
of this so the first
will be cushing syndrome
hyperparathyroidism
hypothyroidism and
hyperthyroidism so
for those thyroid
disorders you're going
to want to order a
TSH to check that.
Aorticorocation, so that's
mainly in younger kids, but
it also can be diagnosed
in adults. Some medications
can also cause this, so
some of the more common ones
are going to be oral
contraceptives, chronic NSAID use,
corticosteroids, and
decongestants. Also,
illicit drug use,
specifically cocaine,
can be a common cause
of hypertension.
And it's one that you
might see, like, on board
exams. Sometimes I like
to use the cocaine use.
And then there's
pheochromocytomas,
primary aldosteronism.
So primary aldosteronism
is going to be
the presence of primary
mineral corticoid
excess, specifically
aldosterone, and usually
presents with a triad
of hypertension,
unexplained hypokalemia,
and metabolic alkalosis.
Then there's obstructive
sleep apnea. So
this one is commonly
seen in patients that
have obesity, and
they're going to have
disordered breathing
during their sleep.
And lastly, there's
stenosis of the renal artery
and fibromuscular dysplasia.
So these renal vascular
diseases are typically
presenting with a sound of
an abdominal bruit when
you do that abdominal exam.
And then specifically for
fibromuscular dysplasia,
this usually occurs
in younger adult
females, and you'll
see a string of beads
appearance of the
renal artery on CT.
Then we have white coat
hypertension, which is
when the blood pressure
readings are going to
be high in office, but
then when they measure
it at home, it's
normal. and then masked
hypertension, which is
going to be the opposite.
So in office, the
blood pressure readings
are normal, but when
they take their blood
pressure out of
office, it's elevated.
So in the case of white coat
hypertension and
masked hypertension,
we would use the ambulatory
blood pressure measurement.
So like we mentioned
before, it's this kind of
cuff that's worn over the
course of 24 to 48 hours.
So the patient keeps it
on and then that cuff
keeps measuring the blood
pressure about every
30 minutes. So this is
used when we see a patient
that has some kind of
discrepancy between their
home and office blood
pressure measurements.
Next we have resistant
hypertension. So this is defined
as when the blood pressure
remains greater than or
equal to 140 over 90,
despite use of three or more
antihypertensive medications
of different classes, including
a diuretic at maximum
tolerated dose, or when the
blood pressure is achieved
through 4-plus medications.
So that would mean that
it would be considered
a controlled resistant
hypertension.
So some of the causes of
this, like we talked about
before, could be secondary
hypertension. hypertension,
so this could be potentially
something that was
missed, and you'd have to
kind of go back and do some
more lab work, redo
your physical exam more
thoroughly to see, you know,
what could be causing it.
Another cause could
be noncompliance with
medications. If the
patient's not taking them as
prescribed, we can get
resistant hypertension.
And also diet.
If the patient is
noncompliant with lifestyle
changes, and they're
supposed to decrease
their sodium, however,
they continue to eat a
lot of fast food diet,
then this could be
another potential cause.
And then there's hypertensive
crisis. So there's two
different categories within
hypertensive crisis. The
first is hypertensive urgency.
So this is severe hypertension,
meaning that the systolic
is greater than or
equal to 180, and the diastolic
is greater than or equal
to 120, with no signs of
acute end organ damage. And
then there's hypertensive
emergency. So this is severe
hypertension. Again, same
greater than or equal to 180
over greater than or equal
to 120 with evidence of
acute end organ damage. So
some of the things that this
can include are going to be
signs of encephalopathy or
stroke, signs of retinal
hemorrhages or papilledema,
signs of myocardial
infarction, heart failure,
aortic dissection,
kidney injury. So
these are some of the
things you want to keep
in mind if your patient
comes in with very
elevated blood pressure
into the emergency
room or into clinic.
Some of the causes of
hypertensive crisis
can include a
secondary hypertension,
any kind of medication
non-compliance, sudden
discontinuation of short-acting
antihypertensive medications,
So, for example, beta
blockers or clonidine,
MAO inhibitors and tyramine
-rich foods, and recreational
drug use. So, the common
one would be cocaine use.
So, primary hypertension
risk factors can be divided
into modifiable or non
-modifiable risk factors.
So modifiable are going
to be the things that you
can work on with your
patients and counsel them on
to try and improve. And
then the non-modifiable risk
factors are going to
be the things that your
patient can't really change
about their life. So the
modifiable are going to
include things like obesity,
a high-sodium or unhealthy
diet, any excess alcohol
intake, physical
inactivity, and smoking. And
then the non-modifiable is
going to include increased
age, any sort of family
history of hypertension,
race, and low
socioeconomic status.
So with race, something
to keep in mind is that
specifically for your
black patients is going to
be that they have more
common, more severe,
occurring earlier in life
hypertension, and it can
be associated with greater
target organ damage.
So you want to be very
mindful of this when
you're evaluating your
patients of different race.
So all of these risk
factors go in hand with the
cardiovascular disease risk
factors. And so decreasing
those modifiable risk
factors is going to
decrease the risk of
hypertension and in turn also
cardiovascular disease in your
patients. This is why it's
very important work in
trying to help your
patient out with decreasing
those modifiable risk factors
as a future physician.
So now let's think
back to our case
from the beginning
of the lecture.
Think about what
risk factors that
patient had and
which of those are
modifiable and which
are not modifiable.
So some of the modifiable
risk factors that our
patient had included NSAID
use, a sedentary lifestyle,
fast food intake,
which is probably
going to be high in sodium,
our patient was a smoker
and had alcohol intake,
and a high BMI. So these
are the things you can
counsel this patient on.
Some of the non-modifiable
risk factors are going to
include a family history
of hypertension hypertension
as well as race.
So now we have a few
practice questions for you
guys. So for the first
one, a 49-year-old woman
presents for an annual
physical. She has no
history of hypertension,
diabetes, or any cardiovascular
disease, exercises
regularly, has a healthy
diet, doesn't smoke,
doesn't drink alcohol. Her
vitals include blood
pressure of 128 over 84,
heart rate of 72,
respiratory rate 12, and
temperature of 98.4 degrees
Fahrenheit. Replete blood
pressure readings on two
subsequent visits are
similar. Which of the
following is the correct
classification of this
patient's blood pressure?
Is it normal, elevated,
hypertension stage 1,
hypertension stage 2, or
white coat hypertension?
So the correct answer is
going to be C, hypertension
stage 1. If we take a look
at this patient's blood
pressure, their systolic
of 128 falls under the
category of elevated,
whereas the diastolic of 84
falls under the category
of stage 1 hypertension. So
this is just to remind
you that if there's a
discrepancy between
categories in the systolic and
diastolic, we're going to
go with the higher category.
So next we have a 60-year
-old white male with past
medical history of
hypertension, hyperlipidemia,
type 2 diabetes, and heavy
tobacco use presenting to
the clinic for follow-up
of the high blood pressure.
Despite escalating his
antihypertensive regimen, he
has persistently elevated
blood pressure readings.
The only symptom he
has is a headache. He
denies any chest pain.
He's currently taking
four antihypertensive
medications. BMI is 25.
Vitals are unremarkable,
except his blood
pressure is 177 over 120
in the right arm and 179
over 123 in the left
arm. Physical exam is
consistent with an upper
abdominal burry. The
finding is best
explained by which of the
following, aortic correcation,
aortic dissection,
abdominal aortic
aneurysm, renal artery
stenosis, or
obstructive sleep apnea.
So our patient has a
couple of risk factors, has
persistently elevated
blood pressure readings,
so remember if you're taking
three or more antihypertensive
medications you are
considered to have a
resistant hypertension and
one of the causes that we
discussed was secondary
hypertension so we want to start
looking at those underlying
causes. Now on his physical
exam he had an upper
abdominal buoy so that kind
of clues us in more towards
a renal artery stenosis.
Next, we have a 25-year
-old female who presents
to the emergency department
with an episode of
epistaxis associated with
extremely elevated blood
pressure. She has no past
medical history. Her blood
pressure is noted to be
170 over 100 in the ED.
BMI is 24. On physical
exam, there are no heart
murmurs, no abdominal
bruise, no thyromegaly.
Lab workup, including
TSH, serum electrolytes,
blood glucose, and
creatinine is normal.
which of the following
additional tests would you
order next? An ultrasound
of the renal arteries,
polysomnography
for sleep apnea,
a urine drug screen, a full
thyroid panel,
or a lipid panel.
So this patient is presenting
with epistaxis, has
high blood pressure when
has had no prior history,
is a young patient, no
physical exam findings
that are remarkable, no
remarkable lab workup,
findings. So this is kind
of cluing us in more towards
looking into secondary
causes of hypertension.
Remember, we discussed like
one of the things you'll look
into is young patients with
no history. And so this is
kind of cluing us more
towards potential cocaine use.
So the answer choice would
be C, urine drug screen.
For the other answer
choices, for A, ultrasound
of the renal arteries
would be helpful in
diagnosing a renal artery
stenosis, but that's
something we more so
see in older patients.
And on physical exam,
we'd probably hear an
abdominal burry present.
Then for answer choice B,
polysomnography for sleep
apnea. That's incorrect
because usually we
see a patient that has
a much higher BMI. It's
seen in obese patients.
Answer choice D, a full
thyroid panel. So our patient
already had normal TSH, had
no thyromegaly on physical
exam, so it's more unlikely
and probably unnecessary
to go through with ordering
a full thyroid panel.
And then answer choice E,
a lipid panel, that would
more so be indicated
for a patient that we're
doing an initial workup
for, for hypertension.
So again, it's probably
more unlikely. The more
correct answer would be to
check the urine drug screen.
So how are we going to evaluate
a patient that
has hypertension?
So like you learned
in DPR, you're going
to go through your
history, the medical
interview, as you
guys have learned.
So the important
things are going to
be to talk about
those risk factors.
Then you, so you want to ask
about like any prescription
medications, any non
-prescription NSAID use, are
they consuming any alcohol?
Are they smoking? You want
to know how long they've
noticed the hypertension for.
You'll also want to ask
them if they've seen anyone
for this already, if
they've tried taking any
medications in the past.
Are they having any signs
of target organ damage?
So any changes in vision?
And then you'll also
want to know if they have
presence of any other
known risk factors for
cardiovascular disease.
So you want to be asking
them about their past
medical history as well.
So after the history
taking, the next step will
be to do the physical
exam. So like we mentioned,
many patients are going
to be asymptomatic most
of the time. So your
physical exam is going to
be important as you'll
be evaluating for certain
very specific signs of
end organ damage and
potential signs for secondary
causes of hypertension,
if you believe that
that might be the cause.
You're going to be checking
for any established
cardiovascular disease
as well. So here I have
like an example of
what the physical exam
findings could look like
typed out in your notes.
So you're going to want
to document general
findings like body
fat distribution,
how alert they are.
Then an important one is
going to be the fundoscopic
exam. in order to evaluate
for signs of hypertensive
retinopathy. So I have
a picture later on, but
basically you'll see stuff
like flame hemorrhages,
AV nicking, papilledema,
and cotton wool spots.
Then for evaluation of the
neck, you can listen to
the carotids, measure the
neck circumference, which
is going to be more important
for a secondary cause
of hypertension due to
obstructive sleep apnea. You
can check the thyroid and
see if you feel any kind
of enlargement or nodules.
You'll check the heart.
So, you know, one
of the complications
that we'll talk
about a little later
will be left
ventricular hypertrophy.
That can be a finding in
patients that have hypertension.
So something you might
hear is an S4 gallop.
You'll do a lung exam,
abdominal exam. This is
also going to be important
because you'll want
to specifically listen
for any abdominal bruise
that might suggest a
renal artery stenosis.
You'll check the femoral
pulses, the peripheral
pulses, check for any edema,
and do a neurologic exam.
So overall, you're going
to do a pretty thorough
physical exam for your
hypertensive patients.
So after your history and
physical exam, you'll want
to order some labs. So I
have a list here of all the
labs that should be performed
in all patients that
are coming in for initial
evaluation of a newly diagnosed
hypertension. So that's
going to include checking
the electrolytes, checking
BUN and creatinine,
checking fasting glucose and
fasting lipid profile, the
HbA1c, urinalysis, a CBC,
a TSH, and an EKG. And then
I've also linked in this
PowerPoint the 10-year
atherosclerotic cardiovascular
disease risk calculator.
So that's something
that you guys could
just like play around
with. It'll be more
useful when you go
on to your rotations.
But basically, you can
input all the information
on your patient, and it'll
give you a percentage
of developing
cardiovascular disease in
the next 10 years, like
the risk of developing.
So now we have
another question.
A 43-year-old male
presents to the office for
initial evaluation of high
blood pressure. He exercises
regularly, follows a low
-salt diet, but his blood
pressure is still around
154 over 86 in office,
including today. He has no
symptoms or past medical
history. His BMI is 26.
On physical exam, no
vascular breweries are
heard. Peripheral pulses are
plus to and symmetrical,
and heart and lung exams
are unremarkable. EKG
shows normal sinus rhythm.
CBC and CMP are normal.
Which additional
study would you recommend
for the patient?
24-hour cortisol
excretion, lipid panel
and urinalysis,
renal ultrasound,
aldosterone levels,
or polysomnography.
So the answer
choice is going to
be B, lipid panel
and urinalysis.
So this patient is
presenting for an
initial evaluation
of hypertension.
So if you remember from
the lab testing slide,
lipid panel and your
analysis are going to be
in that initial newly
diagnosed hypertension
workup. All of the other
answer choices would be
relevant in a patient
who's being evaluated for a
secondary cause of
hypertension, hypertension,
which would probably
occur later on if we see
that the patient has
resistant hypertension,
for example, or something
else is going on.
So the last thing we're
going to talk about
is complications
of hypertension and
what could happen if
you don't treat it
properly. So we'll start
off with the heart.
Some things that might
occur include left
ventricular hypertrophy,
heart failure.
So if you look on
the right-hand side
of the page, you
have an image of the
pathophys of congestive
heart failure,
and then an image
right below that
on a hypertrophied
left ventricle.
And I know you
guys get lectures
on all of these pathologies.
So this is just here to
make you aware of all of
the things that might result
from hypertension if you
don't treat it. um so you
your patient might also
get cardiomyopathy ischemic
heart disease including
coronary artery disease
and myocardial infarction
atrial fibrillation aortic
aneurysm aortic dissection
carotid artery stenosis
so this is why it's
going to be really important
to manage your patient's
hypertension it's the
most prevalent modifiable
risk factor for premature
or cardiovascular disease.
So you need to make sure
to pay attention to it.
Then we might see some
complications of hypertension
in the brain. So in
these patients, you might
see stroke, transient
ischemic attacks or TIAs,
covenative impairment,
intracerebral hemorrhage. And
then in the eyes, like we
mentioned before for the
physical exam, if you do a
fundoscopic exam, you might
be able to see signs of
hypertensive retinopathy.
So if you look at the
left-hand picture,
there are some signs of
hypertensive retinopathy there
on a fundoscopic exam. So
you see that AV nicking,
cotton wool spots.
And then to the right
of that, you have
the grading for
hypertensive retinopathy
based on the findings
that you see.
So that's just there
for your own knowledge,
and you guys can read
it on your own time.
and lastly we have complications
of hypertension present
in the kidneys so hypertension
can lead to hypertensive
nephrosclerosis and the
way this happens is when
you have chronic increased
blood pressure it leads
to narrowing of the afferent
and the efferent arterioles
and that in hand is
going to lead to reduced
glomerular blood flow, which
leads to potential glomerular
and tubular ischemia. So
then you start getting that
nephrosclerosis and fibrosis.
Long term, this basically
leads to end-stage renal
disease. So you want to
keep in mind that hypertension
is the leading cause of
end-stage renal disease,
especially in African Americans.
So again, this is another
reason why why you want
to make sure you're managing
hypertension and you're
being very careful with it
so in summary the biggest
takeaways are going to be
understanding the definition
of hypertension how to
specifically diagnose and
screen and the different
methods you have for actually
measuring blood pressure
then it's going to be being
able to differentiate between
the different types of
hypertension also you should
know and understand the
risk factors and those which
are modifiable and therefore
you can counsel on and those
which are non modifiable
and then also understanding
how to properly evaluate
a hypertensive patient so
understanding the important
aspects of the history the
physical exam important
findings in the physical
exam and the most important
labs that you should order
on initial evaluation and
lastly just know all the
complications being aware of
the complications of
hypertension on various organs
and here I have my references
so thank you guys for watching
I hope you enjoyed the lecture
there is a part two and I wish
you guys the
absolute best of luck
and here you have the
lecture feedback form